<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- $Id$ -->
<book lang="en-US">
	<bookinfo>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="Kermeta-Manual_figures/KermetaLogo.png"
					format="PNG" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<title>Use case of Kermeta 2</title>
		<subtitle>Finite state machine sample</subtitle>

		<pubdate>Build
			: &version; &buildNumber;
		</pubdate>
		<date>$Date:: $</date>
		
		<author>
			<firstname>Fabien</firstname>
			<surname>Coulon</surname>
		</author>

		<keywordset>
			<keyword>Kermeta</keyword>
			<keyword>metamodeling</keyword>
			<keyword>language</keyword>
			<keyword>dsl</keyword>
			<keyword>FSM</keyword>
			<keyword>sample</keyword>
		</keywordset>

		<abstract>
			<para>In this tutorial we will show how Kermeta 2 can help you to add sematic on your own model, how to transform it to another model and how to build a basic interpreter.</para>
		</abstract>

		<publisher>
			<publishername>INRIA</publishername>

			<address>
				<state>France</state>
				<otheraddr>
					<ulink url="http://www.inria.fr">http://www.inria.fr</ulink>
				</otheraddr>
			</address>
		</publisher>
	</bookinfo>

	<preface id="preface.link">
		<title id="preface.title.link">
			Presentation
			<phrase id="preface"></phrase>
		</title>
		<para>Kermeta action language is a DSL designed to manipulate
			models. However it
			isn't a general purpose language and thus doesn't
			directly offer all
			the libraries to build for example an application 
			with a
			sophisticated GUI.
		</para>

		<important>
			<title>Prerequisite</title>
			<para>Preconditions so that the tutorials could run correctly</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Use an Eclipse Modeling Tools based on a Juno version</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>On Eclipse IDE should be installed Kermeta language plug-in
						based upon a Release version
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>On Eclipse IDE should be installed Maven plug-in</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Eclipse must be started using a JDK (not a JRE). This must be
						specified in the eclipse.ini file using the -vm option.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>Alternatively to the first 3 points, you can use the predefined
				eclipse package with all kermeta tools preinstalled.
			</para>
		</important>
		<important>
			<para>This tutorial serie explain various procedure to acheive some
				goal, however, the attentive reader must know that even if the
				presented procedure work, you may acheive similar results using
				alternative or slightly modifying the proposed procedure because you
				ma decide to use another tool or use it differently. Roughly,
				all
				this tutorial serie is actually about :
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Java compilation, and the support of java compatible language
						like Scala and groovy. (special care to the compilation classpath)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>OSGI/Eclipse packaging and deployment, which requires to take
						care to the jar content and to the runtime classpath (which can be
						different from the compilation classpath !)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>In all cases, there are various ways to compile, package and
				deploy, either using Eclipse builders or using maven.
			</para>
			<para>This tutorial will try to give suggestions and explain the
				underlying process but explaining maven, Eclipse, java, OSGI isn't
				in the scope of this document. The user must be ready to find and
				read the appropriate documentations.
			</para>
		</important>
	</preface>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		To illustrate the use of Kermeta 2, we will see the study case of a Finite state machine(FSM).
		At the end of this tutorial you will know how to use Kermeta 2 for :
		<para> 
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Import a model in Kermeta 2</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Adding constaints on your model</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Browsing your model</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Adding behavior on your model</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Make a running application based on your model</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Define the FSM metamodel</title>
		<para> An IO/state machine  is composed with two kind of elements: states and transitions which linking them. The current state of the machine move between states by following transitions. A transition is followed if the input is read. And if transition is followed the ouput is writed</para>
		<para>
			This example recognizes the "hello!" motif and produces the "world!" motif. Here, we present this finite-state machine in a specific graphical syntax where states are squares and transitions are arrows between squares. Input and outputs are present above transitions. Here, "h/w" says that we consume an "h" to produce a "w"
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata
						fileref="Kermeta-FSMDslTutorial_figures/helloWorldFSM.png"
						format="PNG" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</para>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Getting the FSM sample</title>
		<para>TODO: this is the result of the tuto, so move to the end chapter?</para>
		<para>Kermeta 2 provides a set of examples to show his skills. Among them you can retrieve the FSM sample, which will install Kermeta 2 projects in your workspace. You will find into them, as a support of this tutorial, the working source code. To do this just go in File -> New -> Example and then select "Kermeta 2 FSM sample" in "Kermeta 2 samples"</para>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Models &amp; Metamodel</title>
		<para> TODO: explain how to desgin the fsm model with emf tools </para>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Adding constraints on the model</title>
		<para> TODO: not yet working on K2 but explain the OCL-like feature and for what is it. Ex: not duplicated transitions allowed</para>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Make the machine alive</title>
		<para> TODO: explain how to write the interpreter and what is it</para>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Model transformation</title>
		<para> TODO </para>
		<section id="determinization">
			<title>Determinization</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section id="minimization">
			<title>Minimization</title>
			<para>Delete duplicated states</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>

</book>
			